<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The address of the nonconformist ministers (in and about the city of London) to His Highness the Prince of Orange</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 4 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A551</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21242</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12226452</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12226452</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56525</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26393)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56525)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 621:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The address of the nonconformist ministers (in and about the city of London) to His Highness the Prince of Orange</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Cockerill ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Broadside.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  London --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:56525:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE ADDRESS OF THE <hi>Nonconformiſt Miniſters</hi> (In and about the City of <hi>LONDON</hi>) TO HIS HIGHNESS THE Prince of ORANGE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>WEdneſday, January</hi> 2. divers of the Diſſenting Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in and about <hi>London,</hi> that go under the Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of <hi>Presbyterial</hi> and <hi>Congregational,</hi> to the Number of Ninety, or upwards, attended his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> at St. <hi>James</hi>'s, being introduced by the Earl of <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> the Lord <hi>Wharton,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Wiltſhire.</hi> Their Senſe was repreſented by one of thoſe Miniſters to this effect, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That they profeſſed their grateful Senſe of his Highneſs's Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zardous and Heroical Expedition, which the Favour of Heaven had made ſo ſurprizingly Proſperous, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That they eſteemed it a common Felicity, that the worthy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triots of the Nobility and Gentry of this Kingdom, had unanimouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concurred unto his Highneſs's Deſign; by whoſe moſt prudent Advice, the Adminiſtration of Publick Affairs was devolved in this difficult Conjuncture, into Hands which the Nation and World knew to be Apt for the greateſt Undertakings, and ſo ſuitable to the preſent Exigency of our Caſe.</p>
            <p>That they promiſed the utmoſt Endeavour, which in their Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they are capable of affording, for the promoting the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and moſt deſirable Ends, for which his Highneſs had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56525:2"/>
            <p> That they added their continual fervent Prayers to the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for the Preſervation of his Highneſs's Perſon, and the ſucceſs of his future Endeavours for the Defence and Propagation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Intereſt throughout the Chriſtian World.</p>
            <p>That they ſhould all moſt willingly have choſen That for the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of paying this Duty to his Highneſs, when the Lord Biſhop, and the Clergy of <hi>London</hi> attended his Highneſs for the like purpoſe, (which ſome of them did, and which his Lordſhip was pleaſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcendingly to make mention of to his Highneſs) had their notice of that intended Application been ſo early, as to make their more general Attendance poſſible to them at that time.</p>
            <p>That therefore tho they did now appear in a diſtinct Company, they did it not on a diſtinct Account, but on that only which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to them and to all Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>That tho there were ſome of Eminent Note, whom Age or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Infirmities hindred from coming with them, yet they concurred in the ſame grateful Senſe of our common Deliverance.</p>
            <p>His Highneſs was pleaſed very favourably to receive this Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and to aſſure them, <hi>That he came purpoſely for the Defence of the Proteſtant Religion; and that it was his own Religion, wherein he was Born and Bred, the Religion of his Country, and of his Anceſtors; That he was reſolv'd by the Grace of God always to adhere to it, and to do his utmoſt Endeavours for the Defence of it, and the promoting a firm <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion among all Proteſtants.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Cockerill</hi> at the <hi>Three Legs</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Stocks Market.</hi> MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
